Chapter 35. The mast head.
It was during the more pleasant weather that in due rotation with the other
seamen, my first mast head came round.
In most American whalemen, the mast heads are manned almost simultaneously
with the vessels leaving her port, even though she may have 15,000 mi and more
to sail, air reaching her proper cruising ground. And if after a three,
four, or five years voyage she is drawing nigh home with anything empty in
her, say an empty vial even, then her mast heads are kept mound to the last,
and not till her sky sail poles sail in amongst the spires of the port does she
altogether relinquish the hope of capturing one whale more.
Now, as this business of standing mast heads, a shore or a float, is a very
ancient and interesting one, let us in some measure expatiate here. I take it
that the earliest standards of mast heads were the old Egyptians, because in
all my researches I find none prior to them. For though their progenitors, the
builders of Babel, must doubtless by their tower have intended to rear the
loftiest mast head in all Asia or Africa either, yet the final truck was put to
it, as that great stone mast of theirs may be said to have gone by the board in
the dread gale of God's wrath.
Therefore, we cannot give these Babelbuilders priority over the
Egyptians. And that the Egyptians were a nation of mast head standards is an
assertion based upon the general belief among archaeologists that the first
pyramids were founded for astronomical purposes. A theory singularly supported
by the peculiar stair-like formation of all four sides of those edififices
whereby with predigious long upliftings of their legs, those old astronomers
were want to mount to the apex and sing out for new stars even as the lookouts
of a modern ship sing out for a sail or a whale just bearing in sight. In St.
Stylites, the famous Christian hermit of old times, who built him a lofty stone
pillar in the desert, and spent the whole latter portion of his life on its
summit, hoisting his food from the ground with a tackle. In him we have a
remarkable instance of a dauntless stander of mast heads, who was not to be
driven from his place by fogs or frosts, rain, hail, or sleet, but valiantly
facing everything out to the last, literally died at his post. Of modern
standards of mast heads, we have but a lifeless set, mere stone, iron, and
bronze men, who, though well capable of facing out a stiff gale, are entirely
incompetent to the business of singing out upon discovering any strange sight.
There is Napoleon who upon the top of the column of Van Don stands with arms
folded some 150 ft in the air, careless now who rules the decks below, whether
Louis Phipe, Louis Blanc or Louis the Devil, Great Washington, too stands high
aloft on his towering main mast in Baltimore, and like one of Hercules
pillars, his column marks that point of human grandeur beyond which few mortals
will go. Admiral Nelson also on a capston of gunmetal stands his mast head
in Trfalgar Square. And ever when most obscured by that London smoke token is
yet given that a hidden hero is there.
For where there is smoke there must be fire. But neither great Washington nor
Napoleon nor Nelson will answer a single hail from below. However madly invoked
to befriend by their councils the distracted decks upon which they gaze.
However, it may be surmised that their spirits penetrate through the thick haze
of the future, and describe what schos and what rocks must be shunned.
It may seem unwarrantable to couple in any respect the mast head standards of
the land with those of the sea, but that in truth it is not so, is plainly
evinced by an item for which Obed Macy, the sole historian of Nantucket, stands
accountable. The worthy oed tells us that in the early times of the whale
fishery, air ships were regularly launched in pursuit of the game, the
people of that island erected lofty spars along the sea coast to which the
lookouts ascended by means of nailed cleats, something as fowls go upstairs
in a hen house. A few years ago, this same plan was adopted by the Bay
Whaleman of New Zealand, who upon describing the game gave notice to the
readyman boats neither beach. But this custom has now become obsolete. Turn we
then to the one proper mast head, that of a whale ship at sea. The three mast
heads are kept man from sunrise to sunset, the seammen taking their regular
turns as at the helm, and relieving each other every 2 hours. In the serene
weather of the tropics, it is exceedingly pleasant, the mast head.
Nay, to a dreamy, meditative man, it is delightful. There you stand 100 ft above
the silent decks, striding along the deep, as if the mass were gigantic
stilts, while beneath you, and between your legs, as it were, swim the hugest
monsters of the sea. Even as ships once sailed between the boots of the famous
Colossus at old roads, there you stand, lost in the infinite series of the sea.
With nothing ruffled but the waves, the transed ship indolently rolls. The
drowsy trade winds blow. Everything resolves you into a langor. For the most
part in this tropic whailing life, the sublime uneventfulness invests you. You
hear no news, read no gazettes. Extras with startling accounts of common places
never delude you into unnecessary excitements. You hear of no domestic
afflictions, bankrupt securities, fall of stocks, are never troubled with the
thought of what you shall have for dinner, for all your meals for 3 years
and more are snugly stowed in casks, and your bill of fair is immutable.
In one of those southern whalemen on a long three or four years voyage, as
often happens, the sum of the various hours you spend at the mast head would
amount to several entire months. And it is much to be deplored that the place to
which you devote so considerable a portion of the whole term of your
natural life should be so sadly destitute of anything approaching to a
cozy inhabitiveness or adapted to breed a comfortable localess of feeling such
as pertains to a bed, a hammock, a hearse, a sentry box, a pullpit, a
coach, or any other of those small and snug contrivances in which men
temporarily isolate themselves. Your most usual point of perch is the head of
the tag gallant mast where you stand upon two thin parallel sticks almost
peculiar to whaleman called the tag gallant cross trees. Here tossed about
by the sea the beginner feels about as cozy as he would standing on a bull's
horns. To be sure, in cold weather you may carry your house a loft with you in
the shape of a watchcoat, but properly speaking, the thickest watch coat is no
more of a house than the unclad body.
For as the soul is glued inside of its fleshy tabernacle, and cannot freely
move about in it, nor even move out of it without running great risk of
perishing, like an ignorant pilgrim crossing the snowy Alps in winter. So a
watch code is not so much of a house as it is a mere envelope or additional skin
encasing you. You cannot put a shelf or chest of drawers in your body, and no
more can you make a convenient closet of your watch coat.
Concerning all this, it is much to be deplored that the mast heads of a
southern whale ship are unprovided with those enviable little tents or pullpits
called crow's nests, in which the lookouts of a Greenland whaler are
protected from the inclement weather of the frozen seas. In the fireside
narrative of Captain Sleet, entitled A Voyage Among the Icebergs in Quest of
the Greenland Whale and incidentally for the rediscovery of the Lost Icelandic
Colonies of Old Greenland. In this admirable volume, all standards of mast
heads are furnished with a charmingly circumstantial account of the then
recently invented Crow's Nest of the Glacier, which was the name of Captain
Sleet's Good Craft. He called it the Sleet's crow's nest in honor of himself.
He being the original inventor and patentee and free from all ridiculous
false delicacy and holding that if we call our own children after our own
names, we fathers being the original inventors and patentees. So likewise we
should denominate after ourselves any other apparatus we may beget. In shape
the sleet crow's nest is something like a large tears pipe. It is open above,
however, where it is furnished with a movable side screen to keep to windward
of your head in a hard gale. Being fixed on the summit of the mast, you ascend
into it through a little trap hatch in the bottom. On the after side, or the
side next to the stern of the ship, is a comfortable seat with a locker
underneath for umbrellas, comforters, and coats. In front is a leather rack in
which to keep your speaking trumpet, pipe, telescope, and other nautical
conveniences. When Captain Sleet in person stood his mast head in this
crow's nest of his, he tells us that he always had a rifle with him, also fixed
in the rack, together with a powder flask and shot for the purpose of
popping off the stray naral or vagrant sea unicorns infesting those waters, for
you cannot successfully shoot at them from the deck owing to the resistance of
the water. But to shoot down upon them is a very different thing. Now, it was
plainly a labor of love for Captain Sleet to describe as he does all the
little detailed conveniences of his crow's nest, but though he so enlarges
upon many of these, and though he treats us to a very scientific account of his
experiments in this crow's nest, with a small compass he kept there for the
purpose of counteracting the errors resulting from what is called the local
attraction of all binnacle magnets, an error ascribable to the horizontal
vicinity of the iron in the ship's planks, and in the glacier's case
perhaps to there having been so many broken down blacksmiths among her crew.
I say that though the captain is very discreet and scientific here, yet for
all his learned binnacle deviations, azimuth compass observations, and
approximate errors, he knows very well, Captain Sleet, that he was not so much
immersed in those profound magnetic meditations as to fail being attracted
occasionally towards that well-relenished little case bottle so
nicely tucked in on one side of his crow's nest within easy reach of his
hand. Though upon the whole I greatly admire and even love the brave, the
honest and learned captain, yet I take it very ill of him that he should so
utterly ignore that case bottle, seeing what a faithful friend and comforter it
must have been, while with mittened fingers and hooded head, he was studying
the mathematics a loft there in that bird's nest within three or four perches of the pole.
But if we southern whale fishers are not so snugly housed aloft as Captain Sleet
and his Greenland men were, yet that disadvantage is greatly counterbalanced
by the widely contrasting serenity of those seductive seas in which we
southers mostly float. For one, I used to lounge up in the rigging very
leisurely, resting in the top to have a chat with Quiqu or anyone else off duty
whom I might find there. Then ascending a little way further and throwing a lazy
leg over the topppsil yard, take a preliminary view of the watery pastures,
and so at last mount to my ultimate destination.
Let me make a clean breast of it here, and frankly admit that I kept but sorry
guard. With the problem of the universe revolving in me, how could I, being left
completely to myself, at such a thought engendering altitude, how could I but
lightly hold my obligations to observe all whale ships standing orders, keep
your weather eye open, and sing out every time? And let me in this place
movingly admonish you, you ship owners of Nantucket, beware of enlisting in
your vigilant fisheries any lad with lean brow and hollow eye given to
unseasonable meditiveness, and who offers to ship with the Fedan instead of
Bowitch in his head. Beware of such a one, I say. Your whales must be seen
before they can be killed. And this sunkeneyed young platonist will tow you
10 wakes round the world and never make you one pint of sperm the richer. Nor
are these munitions at all unneeded. For nowadays the whale fishery furnishes an
asylum for many romantic, melancholy, and absent-minded young men disgusted
with the carking cares of earth and seeking sentiment in tar and blubber.
Child Harold not infrequently perches himself upon the mast head of some
luckless disappointed whale ship and in moody phrase ejaculates.
Roll on thou deep dark blue ocean roll.
10,000 blubber hunters sweep over thee in vain.
Very often do the captains of such ships take those absent-minded young
philosophers to task, upgrading them with not feeling sufficient interest in
the voyage, half hinting that they are so hopelessly lost to all honorable
ambition, as that in their secret souls they would rather not see whales than
otherwise, but all in vain. Those young platonists have a notion that their
vision is imperfect. They are shortsighted. What use then to strain
the visual nerve? They have left their opera glasses at home. Why thou monkey?
said a harpooner to one of these lads.
We've been cruising now hard upon 3 years, and thou hast not raised a whale
yet. Whales are scarce as hen's teeth whenever thou art up here. Perhaps they
were, or perhaps there might have been Schos of them in the far horizon, but
lulled into such an opium-like listlessness of vacant unconscious
revery is this absent-minded youth by the blending cadence of waves with
thoughts that at last he loses his identity, takes the mystic ocean at his
feet for the visible image of that deep blue bottomless soul pervading mankind
and nature, and every strange half-seen gliding beautiful thing that eludes him.
Every dimly discovered uprising fin of some undicernable form seems to him the
embodiment of those elusive thoughts that only people the soul by continually
flitting through it. In this enchanted mood, thy spirit ebs away to whence it
came, becomes diffused through time and space like Kramer's sprinkled
pantheistic ashes, forming at last a part of every shore the round globe over.
There is no life in thee now except that rocking life imparted by a gently
rolling ship by her borrowed from the sea, by the sea from the inscrable tides
of God. But while this sleep, this dream is on you, move your foot or hand an
inch, slip your hold at all, and your identity comes back in horror. Over
decartian vortices you hover, and perhaps at midday, in the fairest
weather, with one halfthrottled shriek, you drop through that transparent air
into the summer sea, no more to rise forever. Heed it well, you pantheists.